Guide to the John Hobart Davis Papers, 1832-1920
John Hobart Davis papers 1832-1920
Davis, John Hobart, 1843-1918
1 Linear Foot 400 Items
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of John Hobart Davis, Civil War soldier and bank officer from Portland, Maine, were a gift to the Rubenstein Library in 1986.
Biographical Note
John Hobart Davis, a resident of Portland, Maine, volunteered for a three-year term of service with the U.S. Army in 1861. As a private in F Company of the 13th Maine Infantry Regiment, he was variously stationed at locations in Mississippi, Louisiana, and Washington, D.C. Davis was a clerk, and later was in charge of ordnance and then of supplies. In Washington, D.C., he served in a U.S. Army Hospital in the ordnance department and then as paymaster. He was discharged in December, 1864.
After the war, Davis returned to Portland and became an officer in the Casco Bank. In 1869, he married Jennie E. Constable, and they had two sons, Marshall and Raymond. He died on November 11, 1918.
Collection Overview
The papers of John Hobart Davis span the years 1832-1920, but the bulk of the collection is the Civil War correspondence, 1862-1865. Davis chiefly wrote the letters to his sister, Elisa E. Davis, with a few letters to other family members, such as his brother Frank. Private Davis was stationed at Camp Beaufort, Me. (1861, Dec. - 1862, Feb.); Ship Island, Miss. (1862, Mar. - 1863, Feb.); Fort Jackson, La. (1863, Feb. - Aug.); Pass Manchoc, La. (1863, Aug. -Sept.); Fort Stephens, La. (1863, Oct. - 1864, July); and Washington, D.C. (1864, Aug. - 1865, Apr.).
Topics discussed in the collection include Davis' attitude toward Blacks, especially his prejudice toward Black officers, foraging raids behind enemy lines and the Battle of Blair's Landing, (also known as Pleasant Hill Landing) as well as aspects of camp life, such as guard duty, artillery practice, drills, and practice skirmishes, pay furloughs, sutlers, camp recreation, and breaking up camp. Some letters are illustrated with maps or drawings. Included also are diaries, photographs, and miscellaneous writings.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
United States.--Army.--Maine Infantry Regiment, 13th (1861-1865)
Louisiana -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Mississippi -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Washington (D.C.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Campaigns
Racism
Red River Expedition, 1864
United States.--Army -- Afro-American Troops
Davis, John Hobart, 1843-1918
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series
  - 1861, Dec. - 1862, Feb. (Box 1)
  - 1862, Mar. - Dec.
  - 1863, Jan. - June
  - 1863, July - Dec.
  - 1864, Jan. - Apr.
  - 1864, July - Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1865, 1920
- Writings and Diaries Series, 1860-1874 and undated
  - Writings and Diaries (Box 2)
- Miscellany Series, 1832- 1870 and undated
  - Miscellany (Box 2)